Okay בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is דף ד Daf
Daled and we're in the middle of the discussion about how we
learn out קידושי כסף kiddushei kessef and although the סתם stam of
the גמרא Gemara began it with all of this קיחה קיחה משדה
עפרן kicha kicha misdeh Ephron which is certainly what everybody knows, the
גמרא Gemara here focuses actually on the פסוק pasuk from a father
selling his daughter, which also of course is you can't escape the
whole context of sale there, especially with the similarity to selling his
daughter in slavery and therefore marrying off his daughter. So the גמרא
Gemara picks up at the middle of ג עמוד ב. Gimmel Amud
Bet. The גמרא Gemara says the following, that although you have by
the case of מוציא שם רע, Motzi Shem Ra, the father says,
את בתי נתתי לאיש הזה, Es biti natati la'ish hazeh,
I gave my daughter to this man, that shows his power to
marry her off, and therefore if he's marrying her off presumably the
גמרא Gemara has two questions, or three actually: How do you know
it's with כסף? kessef? How do you know the father when she's
a קטנה ktana and a נערה, na'arah, as the משנה mishna teaches,
that the father marries her off, and that the father keeps the
money? So from the פסוק pasuk of אין כסף ein kessef by
selling to a slave, we learn out that it's with money. How
do we know that he's the one that does it and he's
the one that pockets it? So the גמרא Gemara says, that's because
of את בתי נתתי לאיש הזה, Es biti natati la'ish hazeh, if
he's the one doing it then presumably he's also the one pocketing
it. So the גמרא Gemara says fine, that proves money and the
father does it and the father pockets it, all when she's a
קטנה. ktana. But the משנה, mishna, not our משנה, mishna, משנה כתובות
Mishna Ketubot teaches that it's even true when she's a נערה, na'arah,
between the age of 12 and 12 and a half, while she's
somewhat of an adult, a legal adult, but still under the control
of her father. How do you know at that stage that he
can also do this and pocket the money? So the גמרא Gemara
says like that. So let's pick up with that question. ואימא, V'eima,
says the גמרא, Gemara, it's about exactly in the middle of ג
עמוד ב, Gimmel Amud Bet, right after the פסוק pasuk is quoted,
that little open circle that begins a line, so one line below
that, את בתי נתתי לאיש הזה. Es biti natati la'ish hazeh. So
the גמרא Gemara says ואימא הני מילי קטנה דלית לה יד, V'eima
hani mili ktana d'leit lah yad, when is it that he sells
her, marries her, keeps the money? A minor that doesn't even have
her own hand, meaning she's not yet a legal adult within the
area, within הלכה. halacha. Now our גירסא girsa we have is לקבל
קידושין, likabel kiddushin, she doesn't have her own hand to accept קידושין.
kiddushin. It seems like רש"י Rashi didn't have that word. According to
רש"י Rashi it was just a question that she's not even an
adult at all, she has no legal standing in הלכה. halacha. But
here with our גירסא girsa it means that she cannot be part
of the act of accepting her own קידושין. kiddushin. אבל נערה דאית
לה יד לקבל קידושין, Aval na'arah d'it lah yad likabel kiddushin, a
נערה na'arah that can receive her own קידושין, kiddushin, I'll get back
to that in a minute, but let's for now just say a
נערה na'arah that's already a legal adult, okay, אימא תקדיש איהי נפשה
ותשקול כספה, eima takdish eehi nafshah v'tishkol kaspah,
maybe she can marry herself and she can pocket the money? How
do we know that it's the father? Now the question is, is
the גמרא Gemara saying
that maybe it's only she that can do it, or maybe in
addition to him doing it she should be able to do it?
It's not exactly clear what the גמרא Gemara is asking. Is the
גמרא Gemara saying that he shouldn't do it and only she should
do it, or is it saying even she should be able to
do it when she's a נערה? na'arah? Anyway, let's see what the
גמרא's Gemara answer is. אמר קרא, Amar kra, the verse says, בנעוריה
בית אביה, B'neureiha beit aviha,
in her youth, in her father's house. That's by a פסוק pasuk
that he can annul the vows that she takes while she's still
in her youth. So the גמרא Gemara says כל שבח נעורים לאביה,
Kol shevach neurim l'aviha, all of the benefit of her youth goes
to her father, so therefore
any money that she would get
if she were to have done an act of קידושין kiddushin
would go to her father, if she were to have received the
money of קידושין kiddushin it would go to her father from that
principle. Okay? So we already know the father can marry her off,
presumably we're going to presume that he can do that when she's
a נערה na'arah as well, but the question is how do we
know that if she does it herself that the money goes on
to her father? And that we learn from this פסוק. pasuk. So
the גמרא Gemara says והא דאמר רב הונא אמר רב מניין שמעשה
בת לאב, V'hala d'amar Rav Huna amar Rav minayin shema'aseh bat l'av,
how do you know that earnings of the daughter go to the
father? שנאמר, Shenemar, even when she's a נערה, na'arah, as the verse
says, וכי ימכור איש את בתו לאמה, V'chi yimkor ish et bito
l'amah, if a man sells his daughter as a maid, מה אמה
מעשה ידיה לרבה אף בת נמי מעשה ידיה לאביה, Mah amah ma'aseh
yadeiha l'raba af bat nami ma'aseh yadeiha l'aviha, the same way a
maid, the person who owns the woman as a slave gets her
labor, so the father also gets her labor. Now what the רש"י
Rashi says is like you don't need the גמרא, Gemara, this דרשה,
drasha, to tell me that as a קטנה, ktana, as a minor,
he's entitled to the labor because it's even a קל וחומר. kal
v'chomer. It's just like implicit. If you can sell her as a
slave, sell her מעשה ידיים ma'aseh yadayim to another person, obviously you're
entitled to them or else you wouldn't be able to sell them.
Okay? So therefore clearly as a קטנה ktana he has rights to
her מעשה ידיים. ma'aseh yadayim. But how do we know that even
as a נערה na'arah the father has rights to his daughter's labor?
So even though ironically you cannot sell, he can't sell... So even
though ironically you cannot, well you know, you cannot sell, he can't
sell his daughter when she's a נערה Na'arah as a slave. He
can marry her, though, that's actually a place where there's a lack
of parallel. Once she's a נערה, Na'arah, she cannot be sold as
a slave, but she can still be married off. So even though
he cannot sell her as a slave when she's a נערה, Na'arah,
the extra פסוק, Pasuk, as בתי נתתי, Biti Natati, what's the extra
פסוק Pasuk of וכי ימכור איש את בתו לאמה? Ve-chi Yimkor Ish
Et Bito Le-amah? I don't know what extras that, but anyway, somehow
from that פסוק Pasuk we're דרשן-ing Darshan that even though it's obvious
that when she's a קטנה Ketannah he's entitled to her מעשה ידיה
Ma'aseh Yadeiha or else he wouldn't have been able to sell her
מעשה ידיה Ma'aseh Yadeiha as a קטנה. Ketannah. But not only that,
even as a נערה, Na'arah, he's entitled to her מעשה ידיה. Ma'aseh
Yadeiha. Somehow that פסוק Pasuk is seen as something telling us something
extra, and the extra thing it's telling us is that even as
a נערה, Na'arah, he's entitled to her מעשה ידיה. Ma'aseh Yadeiha. גמר
אמה מעשה ידיה לרבה אף בת נמי מעשה
ידיה לרבה. Gamar Amah Ma'aseh Yadeiha Le-Rabbah Af Bat Nami Ma'aseh Yadeiha
Le-Rabbah. So the גמרא Gemara says, so that's, if that's what we
learn out that he's entitled to her earnings as a נערה, Na'arah,
so the גמרא Gemara says, why not תיפוק ליה מבינעוריה בית אביה?
Tipok Lei Mi-Be-ne-ureha Beit Aviha? If you think this פסוק Pasuk by
הפרת נדרים, Ha-farat Nedarim, בינעוריה בית אביה, Be-ne-ureha Beit Aviha, that he
gets all of her, that it tells us that when she's in
a state of נערה, Na'arah, he gets all the benefit, so why
did you need an extra פסוק Pasuk to tell me he gets
מעשה ידיה? Ma'aseh Yadeiha? Just learn it from this big global statement
that he gets all of the benefits. So the גמרא Gemara says
אלא, Ela, so why didn't you do that? בהפרת נדרים הוא דכתיב.
Be-hafarat Nedarim Hu Di-chetiv. That פסוק Pasuk בינעוריה בית אביה Be-ne-ureha Beit
Aviha tells me that he has a right to annul vows. Okay,
but it doesn't tell me anything else. So הכי נמי בהפרת נדרים
הוא דכתיב. Hachi Nami Be-hafarat Nedarim Hu Di-chetiv. So also when it
comes to keeping the money of קידושין, Kiddushin, that פסוק Pasuk only
tells me he has rights to annul vows. I think we probably
need to put some stuff on the board. Okay, so basically here's
what you have. As a קטנה, Ketannah,
okay, as a קטנה, Ketannah, he can sell her as a, as
a שפחה, Shifchah, as a slave. Okay, I mean עבד עברי, Eved
Ivri, but whatever. Okay, so therefore he obviously has מעשה ידיה. Ma'aseh
Yadeiha. Okay,
so here you have
slave, מעשה
ידיה, Ma'aseh
Yadeiha,
we have קידושין, Kiddushin,
and we have, we have what?
I guess הפרת נדרים.
Ha-farat Nedarim. Thank you, הפרת נדרים. Ha-farat Nedarim. Okay, so for slave,
obviously that's כי ימכור איש Ki Yimkor Ish by קטנה, Ketannah, כי
ימכור איש את בתו.
Ki Yimkor Ish
Et Bito. Okay,
if he can sell her as a slave, obviously he gets מעשה
ידיה. Ma'aseh Yadeiha. How do we know he does the קידושין? Kiddushin?
את בתי נתתי לאיש הזה. Et Biti Natati La-ish Ha-zeh.
How do we know he does the הפרת נדרים? Ha-farat Nedarim? That's
בינעוריה בית אביה. Be-ne-ureha Beit Aviha. Now how do we know these
things apply as a נערה? Na'arah? Well actually as a נערה, Na'arah,
he cannot sell her. Okay, that we, he can only sell her
when she's a קטנה. Ketannah. Okay, so if that's true, how do
we know that he gets מעשה ידיה Ma'aseh Yadeiha if he can't
sell her? So somehow they make a דרשה, Derashah, don't ask me
what, that somehow כי ימכור Ki Yimkor is extra and tells me
that even as a
נערה, Na'arah, even a נערה, Na'arah, he has מעשה ידיה. Ma'aseh Yadeiha.
Okay? But it's a little bit, it's not obvious because he can't
sell her as a, as a slave. So that's what we learn
it out somehow some extra דרשה. Derashah. How do you know הפרת
נדרים? Ha-farat Nedarim? בינעוריה בית אביה, Be-ne-ureha Beit Aviha, that's נערה Na'arah
anyway. So the only thing that we still don't know is how
do you know by קידושין Kiddushin that he's entitled to marry her
and to keep the money, or another way of looking at it
is, how do you know that if she marries herself, maybe at
least then she should be able to pocket the money? How do
you know he gets the money? And if you say, well בינעוריה
בית אביה Be-ne-ureha Beit Aviha tells me that he has all the
rights, so the גמרא Gemara is saying but this can't tell me
he has all the rights by נערה Na'arah because then this פסוק,
Pasuk, you wouldn't have needed this פסוק. Pasuk. The fact that you
need this פסוק, Pasuk, obviously this פסוק Pasuk בינעוריה בית אביה Be-ne-ureha
Beit Aviha is limited to הפרת נדרים. Ha-farat Nedarim. You cannot use
it to tell me a global principle that he has all these
rights because we see you needed a special פסוק Pasuk to teach
me מעשה ידיה. Ma'aseh Yadeiha. So we still have to know, how
do you know by קידושין Kiddushin that he's entitled to keep the
money if she marries herself? Okay? Pretty clear to people? All right.
So, so let's take a look. הכי נמי, Hachi Nami, okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says הכי נמי בהפרת נדרים, Hachi Nami Be-hafarat Nedarim,
וכי תימא נילף מינה. Ve-chi Teima Nilaf Minah. Ah, but okay, but
now we know he gets the מעשה ידיה. Ma'aseh Yadeiha. If he
gets the מעשה ידיה, Ma'aseh Yadeiha, if he gets her earnings, logically
he should be able to keep money that she gets in the
act of קידושין. Kiddushin. So the גמרא Gemara says הכי נמי נילף
מינה, Hachi Nami Nilaf Minah, so the גמרא Gemara says no, I'm
sorry, first, excuse me, wrong way, נילף מינה, Nilaf Minah, let's first
go from if he can annul her vows, he could, he could
get her קידושין. Kiddushin. So the גמרא Gemara says ממוני מאיסורי לא
ילפינן, Mamoni Me-issuri Lo Yalfinan, no you can't learn monetary issues from
like איסור והיתר, Issur Ve-heter, the right to annul vows doesn't teach
you that he's entitled to any money. וכי תימא תיליף מקנסא, Ve-chi
Teima Tilif Mi-kenasa, ממוני מקנסא לא ילפינן. Mamoni Mi-kenasa Lo Yalfinan. Ah,
what about another thing? When he actually the whole thing that we
quoted before about the case about the, you know, מוציא שם רע,
Motzi Shem Ra, right... Is that she's a נערה naarah and who
gets the money when it basically turns out the guy is lying,
right? Who gets the money? The father, right? So therefore, so why
not learn out now? So, I'm sorry, or רש"י Rashi actually says,
I don't know why I said מוציא שם רע, motzi shem ra,
רש"י Rashi actually says אונס ומפתה, ones u'mifateh, but either way it's
also by the מוציא שם רע, motzi shem ra, right? ונתנו לאבי
הנערה. v'natnu l'avi ha-naarah. Anyway, but there's a case about קנס, knas,
okay? So you have מוציא שם רע motzi shem ra and אונס
ומפתה, ones u'mifateh, rape and seduction, and all those cases the הלכה
halacha is the Torah says that the father gets the קנס. knas.
So that's money, so why not learn out from the fact that
he gets the money here that she should get the money by
כסף קידושין? kesef kiddushin? Okay? So the גמרא Gemara says, no. ממונא
מקנסא לא ילפינן. Mamona miknasa lo yalfinan. You can't learn anything out
from קנס knas because קנס knas is basically the idea of a
punishment. It starts with the idea not the guy owes money, but
we're going to give him a monetary fine and a punishment. So
therefore the fact that the father receives that money doesn't prove that
things that are not about punishments and fines but just כסף קידושין,
kesef kiddushin, maybe she's marrying herself, maybe she should be entitled to
that. Now again, you could still ask about a logic. She's the
one that got raped, she's the one that got slandered, although you
could say maybe the father's reputation got slandered as well, but she's
certainly the one that got raped. And nevertheless the money is going
to the father, but no that the קנס knas wasn't the payment
for the rape, the קנס knas was just a punishment. You can't
prove anything from it. So money that actually is somehow money deserved,
maybe that would go to her and maybe that's the כסף קידושין.
kesef kiddushin. So the גמרא Gemara says okay, but it's not just
קנס. knas. The גמרא Gemara says וכי תימא נילף מבושת ופגם? v'chi
teima neilef m'boshet u'p'gam? קנס knas is an additional monetary fine. בושת
boshet and פגם p'gam are the real compensation payments for the rape,
right? בושת boshet is the embarrassment, the shame that comes with it,
and the פגם p'gam is the actual injury. You could also talk
about צער tsar which is the psychological, okay? So that's the actual
payment. Rape is treated in הלכה halacha basically like assault, like a
case of physical person injury, okay, so no better no worse. But
again, the Torah is quite revolutionary about rape that actually says that
the girl is a victim, the woman is a victim and she's
not to be blamed for it, which as we know in ancient
societies and some societies today is not the way it's treated. But
it does not but the punishment for rape, look, the same way
if somebody assaults somebody and tears off their arm right nowadays they'd
go to prison and in the Torah all you do is you
pay for it, right? So it's a little bit strange that it's
only treated as it were civilly and not criminally. So that's true
about assault and it's true about rape. Okay, but anyway you have
בושת boshet and פגם p'gam but that is actually payment for the
actual injury, that's actually compensation, and that goes to the father. So
if that goes to the father, even money that's deserved and compensation
to the girl goes to the father, so we should be able
to learn out כסף קידושין kesef kiddushin even when she marries herself
goes to the father. Again in the case of a נערה. naarah.
Yeah, right, it's a נערה. naarah. If she's older then it goes
to herself, right? Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says okay, אבושת ופגם
דאבויה שייך בגופא. a'boshet u'p'gam d'avua shaich b'gufa. No, no, no, he
has rights to her בושת boshet and פגם. p'gam. Why does he
have rights to her בושת boshet and פגם? p'gam? So okay, here's
a very disturbing רש"י. Rashi. רש"י Rashi isn't disturbing, he's describing a
disturbing assumption of the גמרא. Gemara. If you look at רש"י, Rashi,
רש"י Rashi says like this, דאבויה שייך בגופא, d'avua shaich b'gufa, about
eight lines from the bottom. רש"י Rashi says שיש לו דין חלק
בהן שיש לו בידו לבושה ולפגמה בשביל ממון שיתנו לו דאי בעי
מסר לה למנוול ומוכה שחין. she-yesh lo din chelek bahen she-yesh lo
b'yado l'vosha u'l'fogma bishvil mamon she-yitnu lo d'i baei masar lah l'menuval
u'mukei shchin. רש"י Rashi says look, the father basically can decide to
take a, forgetting meaning there's the כסף קידושין, kesef kiddushin, like in
all government, right, there's the money that officially you get paid for
the job and then there's all the money that changes hands below
the table. So therefore whether or not however we decide about who's
entitled to the פרוטה prutah that the girl gets as a נערה,
naarah, okay, רש"י Rashi says someone could basically pay the father a
lot of money to agree to marry his daughter off to him,
right, that's the money that changes hands in the back rooms, that's
not the official כסף קידושין. kesef kiddushin. So therefore רש"י, Rashi, so
therefore basically he could have made, this is disgusting but anyway, he
could have made money by marrying when she was undamaged goods by
marrying her off and made a lot of money and now he
can't. So that's why he's entitled to the compensation. Of course but
then the money in the house כסף קידושין, kesef kiddushin, if that's
because of how he could have married her off, then how could
he not get the כסף קידושין? kesef kiddushin? Isn't that at least
as obvious? So it's a very, this is where the גמרא Gemara
gets very murky, but anyway we'll end. just going to go for
it. I mean תוספות Tosfos has a way of explaining it, he
could have married her off as a קטנה, Ketanah, and that, anyway
let's just keep on moving. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this: אלא, Ella, meaning he can't marry off as a נערה Na'arah
to... Yeah, but then what does it mean אבוך שייכא בקמה? avuch
shayeicha bekama? I don't want to get into it. It's complicated if
you try to unpack this. Okay, but the basic point of it
is is that, yes, he gets all of these payments, but somehow
maybe he still doesn't get כסף קידושין Kesef Kiddushin when... The way
תוספות Tosfos says is that if he marries her off, like he
could get all these types of things, okay, because he could marry
her, but maybe still if she's marrying herself, maybe at least in
that case when she's marrying herself he should pocket the כסף קידושין.
Kesef Kiddushin. Okay, all the other cases we understand he has rights,
but at least when she's marrying herself she should pocket the כסף
קידושין. Kesef Kiddushin. But he's allowed to marry her off as a
נערה? Na'arah? Yes, yes, true. תוספות Tosfos is then, what is it,
asking that question? Yeah, he can marry her as a נערה Na'arah
and that's why he's entitled to בושת Boshes and פגם, Pegam, because
he can still marry her and get money for her and all
those types of things. But in the scenario where she marries herself,
not where he marries her. Right, not where he marries her. Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says אלא מסתברא. Ella Mistavra. Okay, so we
still don't know how we know in... when she... in the case
where she's marrying herself as a נערה, Na'arah, how do we know
that he pockets the money? So the גמרא Gemara says אלא מסתברא,
Ella Mistavra, it makes sense, דכי קממעיט, Dechi kamemayeit, we're going back
to the פסוק Pasuk of אין כסף, Ein Kesef, right, יצאה חנם
אין כסף, Yatzah chinam ein kesef, יציאה דכותה קממעיט. Yetzi'ah dechvasah kamemayeit.
It's comparing a similar case. So by אין כסף Ein Kesef it
says the master doesn't get money, but in another case somebody else
would get money. So the גמרא Gemara is finally just saying, yeah,
but that somebody else, the logical parallel is not that she herself
would get money, the parallel to the master getting money is the
other person who has control over her. So we're back to that
פסוק Pasuk about אין כסף, Ein Kesef, that when she goes away
from the master in a case of being sold as a slave,
the master doesn't get money, but when she goes away from the
father, the father gets the money. Now when the father sells it,
you don't need a פסוק Pasuk for that. The father basically has
rights to marry her, so of course he's going to pocket the
money. So the פסוק Pasuk would be telling you even when she
married herself. Okay, by the way, right at this stage we're quite
far from our immediate focus about קידושין, Kiddushin, right, it's no longer
about how do you know קידושין Kiddushin is with כסף, Kesef, how
do you know the father has rights to do קידושין, Kiddushin, it's
like a lot of effort right now just to deal with the
one case that when she marries herself, how do you know that
he's the one that pockets the money? Okay, and in the end
we're just getting it from this פסוק Pasuk about אין כסף. Ein
Kesef. That it's not... that in the case of the slave, no
money goes to the master, but in the case of marriage, the
money always goes to the father, whether it's a קטנה Ketanah or
a נערה. Na'arah. So the גמרא Gemara says והא לא דמיא האי
יציאה להאי יציאה? Veha lo damya hai yetzi'ah lehai yetzi'ah? One minute,
what's even the comparison? Leaving the master's not the same as leaving
the father after קידושין. Kiddushin. התם נפקא לה מרשות אדון לגמרי Hasham
nafkah leh me'reshus adon legamrei in one case she's completely away from
her previous master, והכא אכתי מיחסרא מסירה לחופה. Vehocha achati michsra mesirah
lechupah. So here, as long as she has not been given over
to the חופה, Chupah, as long as she hasn't entered into the
house of the husband, her father still... that's all of this point.
While she's a נערה, Na'arah, even after קידושין, Kiddushin, he still has
all of these rights, because קידושין, Kiddushin, remember, does not really change
her lived status, her lived reality is still in her father's house
until נישואין. Nisuin. So how could we learn from this פסוק Pasuk
when he leaves this master, she, you know, the father gets the
money? She's not leaving the father's control at קידושין. Kiddushin. So the
גמרא Gemara says no, לאפרושי נדרים מיהא נפקא לה מרשותיה. Leafroshay nedarim
mi'a nafkah me'reshusei. There's a little bit of a change of status
when it comes to annulling vows, דתנן De-Tnan נערה מאורסה, Na'arah me'orasah,
when she's a נערה Na'arah and she's betrothed, אביה ובעלה מפירין נדריה.
Aviha u'ba'alah meferin nedareha. He cannot annul the vows on himself, he
can only annul the vows together with her husband. Okay, now that's
not even really leaving his control, because he still has control, it's
a shared control, but he's not even losing, you know, full control
in any one area. So it is a little bit of an
interesting comparison, leaving the master and leaving the father, because the גמרא's
Gemara like right, she doesn't really leave the father after betrothal. All
the more reason why he should get the money. All the more
reason why she should get the money, that's a good point. That's,
I mean, right, it makes the parallel stranger that we learn קידושי
כסף Kiddushay kesef from there, because it's not a parallel model for
קידושי כסף, Kiddushay kesef, but you're right, once we're assuming קידושי כסף,
Kiddushay kesef, all the more reason he should get the money. Okay,
so that was a little complicated, but bottom line is we're learning
it out very much, you can't go through this גמרא Gemara even
if you get a little confused without getting the message that the
model is selling your daughter as a slave, right, as a model
for קידושין Kiddushin and that again, and as a קידושי כסף Kiddushay
kesef it very much that transactional model. In particular the גמרא Gemara
statement about בושת Boshes and פגם. Pegam. Sometimes the model is freeing
your daughter as a slave. Well, you're freeing her from your ownership
over her and handing her over to the next guy. Right, but
like the אין כסף, ein kesef, it's not bringing into slavery. Correct,
correct. But it's still... I'm not focusing on the slavery part, I'm
focusing on the sale part, right, you know? So, yes. All right,
yeah. Can you make some... is there some element of that, the
cost and the effort that he made in raising the child, is
being compensated? Yeah, I mean, you can, yeah. I mean, look, there
certainly was a reality that, you know, that daughters would not go
ahead and provide, you know, for their... would not go and earn
money and provide and therefore they were seen as like a financial
burden essentially, you know, and the father had to primary worry was
to marry her off, right, so to somebody who would provide for
her. So I mean obviously the irony is that of course that
they would be taking care of so much of the domestic responsibilities,
you know, in terms of helping the mother, but anyway those are
certainly economic realities, but it's still a question about how you're framing
exactly, you know, this transaction, you know? But you are right, it's
an interesting way of thinking about it. Look, the strange thing is,
it is strange, right? Because on the one hand, you
know, we talk about it as a sale, and as I was
saying is that in the... from the time... in the תורה, Torah,
it's like was this 50 כסף, kesef, which was 200 זוז, zuz,
which is a lot of money because then you say, well, you
know, I mean, he's raising her, she's not going to be... she
didn't earn money for the family, etc. The irony is that what
changes is that when it becomes symbolic, then the financial burden really
shifts completely to the father, right? He's the one that has to
provide a large dowry if he wants to, like, you know, marry
her off, right, to a particular guy, right? So then it sort
of changes who's paying who in a certain way.
Sure though, right? Because it's a קידושין kiddushin and then... then he
sort of... Right. Back to the dowry.
Well, that's the irony, the what the כתובה ketubah becomes, right? I
mean, yeah, the כתובה ketubah is a certain type of a balance
of the groom's financial obligations in the case of divorce, and then
also what the bride is bringing into the marriage right now, right?
And there's somewhat, you know, so there is somewhat like a... you
know, it's less of a sale because like there's... there's money being
brought in from the bride's family, but then there's money being promised
on the groom's side. So yeah, it's important to appreciate that sort
of that more complexity. All right, so let's continue. The גמרא Gemara
says like
this. Okay. והאי ויצאה חנם אין כסף, Vehai veyatza chinam ein kasef,
is that what ויצאה חנם veyatza chinam is coming to tell me?
הא מיבעי ליה לכדתניא, Ha mibaei lei lechadataiya, we need the teaching
what the ברייתא brayta tells me. דתניא, Detanya, taught in the ברייתא,
brayta, ויצאה חנם, veyatza chinam, אלו ימי בגרות, elu yemei bagrut, that
she goes free when she's a בוגרת bogeret at like 12 and
a half or when she and when she has her, you know,
her physical signs of maturity. אין כסף, Ein kasef, without money. So
the extra word of אין כסף, ein kasef, I mean, if it's
חנם, chinam, why not אין כסף? ein kasef? It's redundant. אלו ימי
נערות, Elu yemei naarut, not even as a בוגרת, bogeret, even as
a נערה naara she goes free. So it's not to tell me
this הלכה halacha that the... that a parallel case that there's קידושי
כסף. kiddushei kesef. It's coming to tell me the double language that
she goes free even as a נערה. naara. So אמר רבינא, Amar
Ravina, no, אם כן לימא קרא אן כסף, im ken limarkra an
kesef, or אין ein without a יוד. yud. מאי אין כסף, Mai
ein kasef, spelling it with the extra יוד, yud, tells me I
can learn two things. Number one is the phrase, extra phrase אין
כסף ein kasef tells me she goes free from subservience to slavery
as a נערה, naara, and the extra יוד yud tells me אין
כסף לאדון זה ויש כסף לאדון אחר, ein kesef leadon zeh veyesh
kesef leadon acher, ומניהו אב. umanihu av. That it tells me that...
of course it's a דרש. drash. Tells me that... that's what they...
they want to learn multiple דרשות, drashot, they make up hypotheticals about
what the פסוק pasuk could have said. Okay, anyway, so that tells
me that there's another case where money changes hand,
which is the case where she's married off. Okay, now the גמרא
Gemara actually for once asks, really? How can you learn that from
this יוד? yud? The יוד yud isn't really even extra. וממאי דדרשינן
הכי, Umimai dedarshinan hachi, what entitles you to make a דרש drash
based on that יוד yud which doesn't look extra to me and
you? דתניא, Detanya, taught in the ברייתא, brayta, וזרע אין לה. vezera
ein lah. This is about a wife of a... of a בת
כהן bat kohen who marries
a... you know, a ישראל. yisrael. And if she has no children
after the marriage... no, no, it's the opposite. No, is that right?
The wife of a ישראל yisrael who married a כהן? kohen? No,
it's וזרע אין לה ושבה אל בית אביה כנעוריה, vezera ein lah
veshava el beit aviha kineureiha, right? מלחם אביה תאכל. Milechem aviha tochal.
So it's a בת כהן bat kohen who marries a ישראל, yisrael,
right? בת כהן bat kohen who marries a ישראל, yisrael, that in
that case if after her husband dies, so if she has no,
as it were, tie to the husband's family, no living children, then
she's seen as going back to her father's house and she continues
to eat and she goes back to eating תרומה. truma. Okay, now,
but it just says she has no seed. אין לי אלא זרעה,
Ein li ela zarah, I only know her own seed. זרע זרעה
מנין, Zera zara minayin, let's say she has no living children but
she has grandchildren. How do I know that that would also constitute
a seed? תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar וזרע אין לה. vezera ein lah.
So now we're going to דרש drash from the... and from we're
going to play on the word אין. ein. עיין לה, Ayen lah,
like as if it was written with an עין. ayin. Look into
her. ואין לי אלא זרע כשר, Ve'ein li ela zera kasher, זרע
פסול מנין. zera pasul minayin. How do I know even if it
was a... invalid זרע zera like for example a ממזר mamzer רש״י
Rashi says that that would still be considered enough like you know
her family that she would not go back to her father's house?
תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar זרע אין לה, zera ein lah, עיין לה,
ayin lah, the idea of investigate means any circumstance. Okay so the
גמרא Gemara says והאפיקתה ve'afikta
לזרע זרעה. lezera zarah. גמרא Gemara says how do you use אין
לה ein lah to tell me both grandchildren and this case of
זרע פסול? zera pasul? You already you know you already used it
for the grandchildren. This is זרע זרעה לא איצטריך. zera zarah lo
itztarich. For grandchildren you really didn't even need the פסוק. pasuk. בני
בנים הרי הם כבנים. benei banim harei hem kevanim. Children of grandchildren
are like your own children. איצטריך לזרע פסול. itztarich lezera pasul. Okay
so the extra אין לה עיין לה ein lah ayin lah is
even for a case of you know of of of illegal children.
Okay anyway illegitimate children. So anyway you see that the extra יוד
yud teaches you that you can make the דרשה. derasha. So here
too the extra יוד yud teaches us that you know אין כסף
ein kesef for you know אין כסף ein kesef teaches you two
things. Number one is she goes free at נערה na'arah and the
extra יוד yud teaches you that there's such a thing as כסף
קידושין kesef kiddushin and money you know in a different type of
a sale money changes hands and it's כסף קידושין.
kesef kiddushin. He said really technically it's not an extra יוד. yud.
Right. That's what we're going to get to now. What? It's not
really an extra.
Well now that's what we're going to say. והתנא גופא מנא ליה
דדריש הכי. Vehatanna gufa mena lei dedarish hachi. How did the תנא
Tanna learn out since why do you think that what makes you
think that יוד yud is extra? Right. Okay you proved me the
תנא Tanna did it by זרע אין לה zera ein lah but
where did the תנא Tanna get that idea from? כתיב Ktiv because
the verse says מאין בלעם me'ein Bil'am ומאין יבמי. ume'ein yivmi. So
you see the word אין ein can appear without a יוד. yud.
Of course that's when it's word מאין me'ein but nevertheless לא כתיב
ביוד lo ktiv beyud והכא כתיב ביוד. vehacha ktiv beyud. So here
we have a extra יוד. yud. שמע מינה לדרשה הוא דאתא. Shema
mina lederasha hu de'ata. Fine just got to go with the flow.
ואיצטריך למכתב. Ve'itztarich lemichtav. Now that we have established that we ask
the question which we should have asked all along because we said
why not prove מהפרת נדרים mehafarat nedarim and קנס knas and פגם
pegam that she keeps the money? Well the more obvious question is
why not just prove from the fact that that he gets her
מעשה ידיה ma'aseh yadeiha that he gets her money? Like I mean
if her earnings he gets to keep so her כסף קידושין kesef
kiddushin he should get to keep. So now the גמרא Gemara is
going to turn to that. ואיצטריך למכתב קידושיה לאביה ואיצטריך למכתב מעשה
ידיה לאביה. Ve'itztarich lemichtav kiddusheiha le'aviha ve'itztarich lemichtav ma'aseh yadeiha le'aviha. It
has to write both. דאי כתב רחמנא קידושיה לאביה De'i ktav Rachmana
kiddusheiha le'aviha if it had said that the כסף קידושין kesef kiddushin
she gets goes to her father הוה אמינא משום דלא טרחה בהו
hava amina mishum delo tarcha behu because she didn't she didn't exert
any effort she didn't work to earn it so that goes to
her father like כסף מציאה kesef metziah I guess. But the fact
that she's marrying herself off to this guy okay אבל מעשה ידיה
דקא טרחה בהו aval ma'aseh yadeiha deka tarcha behu but earned money
that she earned the labor of her hands אימא דידה הוה eima
didah hava maybe she should get to keep it. ואי אשמועינן מעשה
ידיה Ve'i ashmo'inan ma'aseh yadeiha if it just said her earnings go
to her father דקא מיתזנה מיניה deka mitzana minei because she's being
fed by her father so he's expecting that she'll earn some money
and that he'll get it right and that's why he ongoing feeds
her she ongoing earns money and there's an implicit reciprocity which obviously
reflects the way that חז״ל Chazal later instituted the in a marriage
that the husband supports her you know pays for her upkeep and
that he keeps her earnings. So the גמרא Gemara is saying is
like I would have assumed that that would have been the logic
behind why the תורה Torah entitled the father to earnings because he's
because he's supporting her and those are two like ongoing an ongoing
support and ongoing earnings.
אבל קידושיה דמעלמא קאתי. Aval kiddusheiha deme'alma ka'ati. קידושין Kiddushin would like
just falls out of the sky as it were okay it's not
something that happens regularly and not something she goes out and earns
so it's not something to be expected is going to happen אימא
דידה הוה Eima didah hava maybe that he gets to keep. צריכא
Tzricha need to tell you both. Okay fine. Now we're going to
go back to saying how he why these פסוקים psukim that she
goes free as a נערה na'arah and she goes free as a
as a בוגרת. bogeret. Once she's going free as a נערה na'arah
why do you have to tell me that she goes free as
a בוגרת bogeret when she gets sold into slavery? Right.
So just when she's a קטנה ktannah the father marries her off
she can't refuse she she has to quote unquote demand. Right. The
only way she can refuse is if
it's the father and then and
then the mother and the brother and then they can do מיאון.
mi'un. Right.
And then down you know right but I saw what you were
going to ask which is a good question is what does it
mean that as a נערה na'arah she can marry herself off? I
mean the way the רמב״ם Rambam actually פוסק posek is is that
the and the גמרא Gemara was pretty clear anyway that as a
that as a נערה na'arah the father can marry her against her
will so she doesn't need to agree to it even as a
נערה. na'arah. If the father's doing it it could be against her
will. The only question remains as a נערה na'arah can she marry
herself off? So the גמרא Gemara we read like sounds like yes.
But the רמב״ם Rambam actually rules
להלכה lehalacha that she can't no meaning according to most if she
marries herself off then it's sort of it's held it's sort of
it's dependent on the father's either approval or veto. If the father
approves it works if he vetoes it doesn't work. Okay but so
that at least fits with the גמרא. Gemara. But the רמב״ם Rambam
rules להלכה lehalacha that even if the father approves of it after
the fact it doesn't work. The only time she can actually directly
participate in the מעשה קידושין ma'aseh kiddushin is if he approves of
it ahead of the fact. So it's still fundamentally really very much
like he's marrying her she's just the one entitled she's almost like
his שליח. shaliach.
You have my רשות reshut to
marry this person go yeah yeah she's never really doing it herself
she's really at most his שליח. shaliach. Okay. The way the רמב"ם
Rambam understands. Others understand that if she marries herself and he approves
after the fact, then that can still work. Okay, but let's move
on. The גמרא Gemara says גופא gufeh ויצאה חנם v'yatza chinam אלו
ימי בגרות elu y'mey bagrus about a woman being sold as a
Hebrew slave. She goes free as a בוגרת. bogeres. ואין כסף, v'ein
kasef, without money, which is redundant. אלו ימי נערות, elu y'mey narus,
even as a נערה. nara. So the גמרא Gemara says לכתוב רחמנא
נערות ולא בעי בגרות. lichtov rachmana narus v'lo ba'i bagrus. Just tell
me she goes free as a
נערה. nara. So obviously she'll that'll happen before she becomes a בוגרת.
bogeres. And she can only be sold as a קטנה. ketana. So
some חכם chacham would say, wow, what if she's sold as a
נערה, nara, she goes free as a בוגרת. bogeres. No, she can
only be sold as a קטנה. ketana. So if she can only
be sold as a קטנה, ketana, right? And she goes free as
a נערה, nara, so there's no point of saying she goes free
as a בוגרת. bogeres. So the גמרא Gemara says, no. אמר רבא
בזה ולמד על זה. amar Rabba bazzeh u'limad al zeh. You're right,
but if you would have had only one phrase, you would have
said the phrase meant בגרות. bagrus. So you needed two phrases to
say, not only a בוגרת, bogeres, even a נערה. nara. Alright, because
again, you would have just applied the phrase to the to the
latest stage. The double phrase tells you the earlier stage.
But does she need it לגופא, l'gufeh, ויצאה חנם? v'yatza chinam?
No, what ויצאה חנם v'yatza chinam means is she goes free. At
at what stage? When does she go free? So that's what it's
telling me. So I would have said the Torah is very strange.
It says she goes free when. So the only stage חז"ל Chazal
sort of bring their lens into it and they say, when does
she go free? So it must be when she's already an adult,
and so that's בגרות. bagrus. And then the next חידוש chiddush is
even a little bit before being a full adult. All right. So
the גמרא Gemara says בזה ולמד על זה bazzeh u'limad al zeh
מידי דהוה אתושב ושכיר. midi d'havai a toshav v'sachir. Like the הלכה
halacha of תושב ושכיר toshav v'sachir again where we're talking about a
co about תרומה terumah going back to a תרומה terumah theme. דתניא,
d'tanya, we've learned in a ברייתא. braitah. תושב, toshav, it says תושב
כהן ושכיר לא יאכל בו. toshav kohen v'sachir lo yochal bo. The
תושב, toshav, the dweller of a כהן, kohen, and his hired hand
cannot eat his תרומה. terumah. So who are these people? Because his
עבד כנעני eved kna'ani can eat תרומה terumah because his עבד כנעני
eved kna'ani is his property. But you know who can't eat תרומה?
terumah? His עבד עברי. eved ivri. Even though you say, oh he's
more Jewish. Yeah, but he's more Jewish but he's not his property.
So because he's not his property, he can't eat the כהן's kohen
תרומה. terumah. תושב toshav זה קונה קניין עולם. zeh koneh kinyan olam.
That's even an עבד עברי eved ivri that's owned forever, which means
that you know you did the ear with the you know the
awl and whatever and he's owned until the יובל. yovel. שכיר, sachir,
a hired hand, זה קונה קניין שנים, zeh koneh kinyan shanim, even
for just a number of years for the seven years. יאמר תושב
ולא יאמר שכיר. yomar toshav v'lo yomar sachir. Why not just say
that even if the guy that's owned for fifty years doesn't eat
תרומה, terumah, certainly the שכיר sachir doesn't eat תרומה. terumah. ואני אומר
קונה קניין עולם אינו אוכל קונה קניין שנים לא כל שכן. v'ani
omar koneh kinyan olam eino ochel koneh kinyan shanim lo kol sheken.
No. אילו כן, ilu ken, if I had said that, הייתי אומר,
hayiti omer, if there was just one word, if the Torah just
said תושב, toshav, I would have applied that word to the narrower
case. I would have said תושב זה קונה קניין שנים. toshav zeh
koneh kinyan shanim. תושב toshav means the עבד עברי eved ivri for
seven years. אבל קונה קניין עולם, aval koneh kinyan olam, I would
have said the עבד עברי eved ivri for fifty years אוכל, ochel,
that would have eaten. בא שכיר ולמד על תושב. ba sachir u'limad
al toshav. So the fact I have two phrases tells me that
both cases are being covered. And that שכיר sachir means the more
limited hire, that's the suggestion of hire, and תושב toshav means the
more permanent person, the guy for fifty years. Okay, but I needed
both phrases or else I would have said one phrase I would
have applied to the more limited case שאף על
פי שקונה קניין עולם אינו אוכל. she-af al pi she-koneh kinyan olam
eino ochel. Okay. So שכיר sachir tells me that שכיר sachir means
the more limited case and תושב toshav tells me even the fifty
year case, even he doesn't eat.
I suggest was the Torah not תושב ושכיר toshav v'sachir for this.
Correct, correct. They're not explicit enough. Now you could have said, why
couldn't the Torah have been more explicit? But yes, the phrases are
vague enough and I would have applied them to a more limited
case and I needed the second phrase to tell me even a
more extreme case. So here too if it had just said אין
כסף, ain kesef, I would have applied it to בגרות. bogerus. You
know, or חינם, chinam, I would apply to בגרות. bogerus. אין כסף
ain kesef tells me even נערות. narus. אמר ליה אביי, amar lei
Abbaye, so that seems to be a good answer. So let's see
what אביי Abbaye says. אמר ליה אביי מי דמי, amar lei Abbaye
mi dami, you can't compare them. התם תרי גופי נינהו. hasham tray
gufay ninhu. הכא hacha there they're two different people, there's a תושב
toshav and a שכיר. sachir. דכי נמי כתב רחמנא תושב נרצע לא
יאכל, d'chi nami katav rachmana toshav nirtza lo yochal, even if the
Torah had explicitly said an עבד עברי eved ivri with a hole
in his ear, whatever, cannot eat. והדר כתיב אידך v'hadar ksiv idach
and then it would have said an עבד עברי eved ivri for
like six years cannot eat, הוי havay it, so even if it
would have said both and one would have been obvious, even the
one would have been obvious, הוי שכיר מילתא דאתיא בקל וחומר. havay
sachir milsa d'asya b'kal vachomer. That would have been something I could
have learned out from a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. ומילתא דאתיא בקל
וחומר טרח וכתב ליה קרא. u'milsa d'asya b'kal vachomer tarcha u'chtav lei
kra.
The verse is willing to go ahead and say it, meaning it
nothing is lost by saying it. It's not like it's not true.
It might be obvious, but it's not not true. Both the תושב
toshav doesn't eat and the שכיר sachir doesn't eat. So even now
the Torah said both, right, you could say tell me once, so
I would figure out we're talking about both cases. But now that
it has said both, both are true even if one of them
is obvious. How is that different than our case? אלא הכא חד
גופא היא. ella hacha chad gufa hi.
It's this one girl. כי נפקא בנערות בגרות מאי בעיא גביה. ki
nafka b'narus bagrus mai baya gabbeh. If she's going free as a
נערות, narus, she's never going free as a בגרות. bagrus. Okay, so
as opposed to the other case, you're telling me this person goes
free and this person goes free. Oh it's obvious, alright it's obvious,
but I'm telling you anyway. All right, but in this case you
can't tell me she goes free as a בגרות bagrus and she
goes free as a נערות narus but she... She goes free as
a בוגרת Bogeres. *bogeret*. So then what was the פסוק Pasuk *pasuk*
talking about? Okay? So אלא אמר אביי לא נצרכה אלא לבגר דאילונית
*ela amar Abaye lo nitzrecha ela le-vagar de-aylonit*. That's...
there's that woman that becomes a בוגרת *bogeret* without ever having been
a נערה Na'arah, *na'ara*. Who is that? An אילונית Aylonit, *aylonit*. This
woman who has certain, like, doesn't develop certain female characteristics and is
not, not able to have children. But besides not being able to
have children, I mean, I guess I'm not exactly sure what specific
condition it's referring to, but anyway, she sort of doesn't develop some,
you know, basic, certain, certain, so
there's sort of like male
characteristics to her and therefore that woman becomes an adult when she
hits the age of twenty because she never gets like the normal,
sort of, you know, wrought, puberty, sort of, you know, signs of
puberty and whatever that would define her as a נערה Na'arah.
*na'ara*. Until then...
Until then she goes from a קטנה *ketana* to a בוגרת *bogeret*.
When she's nineteen... At nineteen, yes. Well, the גמרא Gemara *gemara* is
going to get to when she can be sold. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara, *gemara* says, okay, so that, she goes free even as
when she, she has בגרות *bagrut* without נערות Na'arut. *na'arut*, בגר דאילונית
*bagar de-aylonit*. סלקא דעתך אמינא *salka datach amina*, בנערות תיפוק בבגרות לא
תיפוק *be-na'arut tipok be-vagrut lo tipok*, maybe she should never go free
because she only goes free at נערות *na'arut*, she never hits נערות
*na'arut*, so even though she leapfrogs to בגרות *bagrut*, maybe she doesn't
go free. קא משמע לן *ka mashma lan* that she does go
free as a בוגרת *bogeret*. Okay, so מתקיף לה מר בר רב
אשי *matkif lah Mar bar Rav Ashi*, ולאו קל וחומר Kal V'chomer.
הוא *ve-lav kal va-chomer hu*? One minute, it's a קל וחומר Kal
V'chomer. *kal va-chomer*. ומה סימנים שאין מוציאין מרשות אב מוציאין מרשות אדון
*u-ma simanim she-ein motzi'in me-reshut av motzi'in me-reshut adon*, so when this
girl gets the, the signs of puberty, the pubic hairs, that does
not free her from her father, she's still a נערה Na'arah *na'ara*,
nevertheless she's freed from her master. בגרות שמוציאה מרשות אב *bagrut she-motzi'ah
me-reshut av*, when this girl becomes a בוגרת *bogeret* or this twenty-year-old
אילונית Aylonit *aylonit* becomes a בוגרת *bogeret*, she's totally independent from her
father, אינו דין שמוציאה מרשות אדון *eino din she-motzi'ah me-reshut adon*, how
much more so should obviously בגרות *bagrut* give her independence. You don't
need the פסוק Pasuk *pasuk* to tell me that. How much more
so does that free her from her master. אלא אמר מר בר
רב אשי *ela amar Mar bar Rav Ashi*, לא נצרכה אלא לעיקר
זבינה דאילונית *lo nitzrecha ela le-ikar zevina de-aylonit*. No, no, no, what
the חידוש *chidush* of the פסוק Pasuk *pasuk* is, it's telling you
about whether you can sell this girl who's an אילונית *aylonit* from
the very outset when she's a minor. סלקא דעתך אמינא דאתיא סימני
נערות הוי זבינה דלא אתיא סימני נערות לא הוי זבינה *salka datach
amina de-atya simanei na'arut havei zevina de-lo atya simanei na'arut lo havei
zevina*. I would have thought a girl that becomes a נערה Na'arah
*na'ara* you can sell, a girl that does not become a נערה
*na'ara* like this girl will never become a נערה *na'ara* you can't
sell. קא משמע לן *ka mashma lan*. What? How would you know
that? So תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* asks that, how you know even as
a, even under twelve, that she's still an אילונית *aylonit*. So תוספות
Tosafot *Tosafot* has a discussion whether you can see סימני אילונית *simanei
aylonit* even at that age. Fine, we won't get into it. קא
משמע לן *ka mashma lan* that yes, you can sell her even
though she'll never become a נערה *na'ara*. So Michael's question, actually, I
have to double-check, but yes, you can sell her even though you
know she'll never become a נערה *na'ara*. Presumably, she would remain a
slave until the age of twenty. That seems to be what the
גמרא Gemara *gemara* is saying.
Can you even sell her then at nineteen because she's still a
קטנה *ketana*? Presumably, yes. היא קטנה *hi ketana*, yes, she's still a
קטנה *ketana*. I mean that is the interesting הלכה *halacha* that this
אילונית *aylonit*, right, is still which is, again, gets to that interesting
point about physical, you know, ba, you know, sexual maturity, right, or
whatever, you know, or, you know, puberty and those issues as opposed
to like here she is a nineteen-year-old completely, you know, much more
of an adult than this twelve-year-old with two pubic hairs and she's
still considered legally a קטנה *ketana*. So that's a very good question
not only about the father selling her, just legally that she's considered
a קטנה *ketana*, right, just because she doesn't have certain, you know,
sexual characteristics. It's a very good point. Okay, so
but, but again, what, what keeps on getting knocked over our head,
right, in this סוגיא Sugya *sugya* is the father's ability to sell
his daughter as a slave and the parallel to that about marrying
off his daughter and this is the model for קידושי כסף Kidushei
Kesef *kidushei kesef*. Now אמר מר בר רב אשי דאמר לאו קל
וחומר Kal V'chomer, הוא *amar Mar bar Rav Ashi de-amar lav kal
va-chomer hu*. According to מר בר רב אשי *Mar bar Rav Ashi*
that said it's a קל וחומר Kal V'chomer *kal va-chomer* that she
goes free as a בוגרת *bogeret*, if she leaves her father's house
as a בוגרת *bogeret*, obviously she goes free as a בוגרת *bogeret*.
האמרינן מילתא דאתיא בקל וחומר טרח וכתב לה קרא *ha amrinan milta
de-atya be-kal va-chomer tarach ve-katav lah kra*. Why is that a question?
We said before that even if something is obvious the פסוק Pasuk
*pasuk* could write it. So maybe that is what the פסוק Pasuk
*pasuk* is telling me that as a בוגרת *bogeret* this woman gets
freed from slavery even if it is obvious. So the גמרא Gemara
*gemara* says no, הני מילי היכא דליכא לשנויי אבל היכא דאיכא לשנויי
משנינן *hani milei heicha de-leika leshinuyei aval heicha de-ika leshinuyei meshaninan*. That's
if you have no other good way to explain the פסוק Pasuk
*pasuk*, but if there is another good way to explain the פסוק
Pasuk? *pasuk* we'll explain it. So we'd rather say the פסוק Pasuk.
*pasuk* is teaching you the חידוש *chidush* that you can sell her
even though she's never going to be a נערה *na'ara* because
for him you don't need the פסוק Pasuk. *pasuk* to tell me
that she goes free when she becomes a בוגרת *bogeret*.
Obviously she goes free when she becomes a בוגרת *bogeret*. Yes Ben,
you had a question? Yes, what, where I,
what I thought was that if a young girl is an אילונית
*aylonit* then, then maybe she can't be sold by the father as
a slave at all. Correct.
Yes. Because she'll never become a נערה *na'ara*. Maybe the תורה Torah
*Torah* only recognizes a girl... תורה *Torah*. Right. Now if you want
an explanation for that other than just a sort of formalistic one,
the whole point of selling the girl to slavery, and this by
the way should be mentioned in general, you know, because maybe it
takes a little bit of the edge off this model that I've
been, that the גמרא Gemara *gemara*'s been banging over your head and
I've been banging over your head about selling as a slave. The
point about selling as a slave in the תורה *Torah*... is ultimately,
it's ultimately the ultimate goal, I mean who can use a slave
under 12 years old? Right? Now again, the פסוקים, Psukim, it's not
at all clear that she's sold under 12 years old and that
she goes free at 12 or whatever. But with the way חז"ל
Chazal understand it, right, who can use, what, okay, and what's she
going to do, a little bit of the cooking and cleaning? I
mean, what's the point? So the basic point though, as the תורה
makes sense, is that he ultimately he should marry her, right, because
it says, you know, so it says, so the whole point is
in the end he doesn't want to marry her and his son
doesn't want to marry her, then she goes free. When it becomes
the age to make that decision, that's פשט Pshat of the פסוקים,
Pesukim? not that she goes free as a נערה, but she goes
free whenever that appropriate age is that it would be determined whether,
you know, my kid just got accepted to these colleges and May
1st is the date. Everybody know that? There's like, after all the
places you get accepted to you have to make your decision by
May 1st, you know, whatever, anyway. Okay, fine. So whatever, like there's
that time where, like, okay, now it's your time. You've had a
lot of time to think about it, she's been in your house
for a while, now make your decision. She's ready to get married,
right? So, you know, and then if he says no and his
son says no, then she goes free. So whatever, so we don't
know exactly when that date is, but so the גמרא Gemara, sort
of says that's נערות. But the whole point of it is ultimately
to lead to marriage. So that's by the way, when we talk
about a girl that's never going to reach, like, you know, sort
of sexual maturity, right, and has this illness which the גמרא, Gemara
you know, whole these questions, right, about yes, קידושין Kidushin is תופס
Tofes by אילונית, but if it's if the guy wasn't aware, it's
קידושי טעות, Kidushei Ta'ut, with the presumption would be that under normal
circumstances, you know, a man wouldn't want to marry a girl that
did not, you know, develop these sexual characteristics and so on. So,
what, maybe that would be completely excluded from this category. So that's
worth explaining what the הוה אמינא Hava Amina might be that that
this אילונית cannot be sold, and it's also important because it takes
a little bit of the edge off this strong model, you know,
the model for קידושי כסף Kidushei Kesef. is selling her as a
slave, so we actually need to counterbalance it with well maybe the
whole point of selling her, by the way, she's an עבד עברי,
Eved Ivri, she's not an עבד כנעני, Eved Kena'ani, and again she's
only very young so what work is she real labor she really
do, right, that maybe the whole model of selling her as a
slave is ultimately a marriage model or the goal is to lead
to marriage. Okay, so that's important to be stated. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, the תנא Tanna מייתי
לה מהכא. maiti lah me'haka. And now finally, we have the, we
have a big, big סוגיא Sugya about the father selling his daughter
as a slave/for purposes of marriage. And now we have this little
סוגיא sugya that we've been quoting from the very beginning about about
the by אברהם Avraham and עפרון. Ephron. So the the תנא Tanna
quotes it from the following source. דתניא, De'tanya, we learned in a
ברייתא, Braita, the idea of קידושי כסף. Kidushei Kesef כי יקח איש
אשה ובעלה, Ki yikach ish isha ube'alah, right, והיה אם לא תמצא
חן בעיניו כי מצא בה ערות דבר. v'haya im lo timtza chen
be'enav ki matza bah ervat davar. Okay, when a man takes a
woman and has sex with her, אין קיחה אלא בכסף. ein kikha
ela b'kesef. Now again, even though פשט Pshat of the פסוק Pasuk
is קיחה kikha זו ביאה, zu biah, which by the way תוספות
Tosfos says as well,
and not, but the other פשט Pshat of the פסוק Pasuk is
we're talking about נישואין, Nissuin, we're not talking about קידושין. Kidushin. Okay,
nevertheless, the גמרא Gemara decides that כי יקח ki yikach means קידושין.
Kidushin. And now what does the word קיחה kikha mean if not
and to say תוספות Tosafos says אין קיחה אלא בכסף, ein kikha
ela b'kesef, with money, דכתיב d'ktiv וכן הוא אומר v'chen hu omer
נתתי כסף השדה קח ממני, natati kesef hasade kakh mimeni, take the
money from me. והלא דין הוא, V'halo din hu, it's a קל
וחומר. Kal Vachomer. ומה אמה עבריה, U'mah amah ivriya, I mean why
do I need a פסוק Pasuk by אברהם Avraham to tell me
that קידושי כסף kesef? that קידושין Kidushin is with כסף? kesef. Again,
because the word קיחה kikha is assumed to refer to קידושין, Kidushin,
not נישואין, Nissuin, and then קיחה kikha with שדה עפרון Sde Ephron
tells me כסף. kesef, Why do I need that? והלא דין הוא,
V'halo din hu, למה לי קרא? lama li kra? קל וחומר. Kal
Vachomer, ומה אמה עבריה, U'mah amah ivriya, when it comes to, again,
now we're comparing again to the Hebrew slave, the girl being sold,
when a girl is sold as a slave שאינה נקנית בביאה, she'eina
niknes b'biah, she's not acquired with sex, נקנית בכסף niknes b'kesef is
acquired with money, זו שנקנית בביאה, zu she'niknes b'biah, this that is
acquired through an act of sex as the remainder of the פסוק
Pasuk says ובעלה, ube'alah,
so אינו דין שתקנה בכסף? eino din she'tikneh b'kesef? How much more
so, like your classic, again, קל וחומר, Kal Vachomer, if it works
here it doesn't work there then the other thing should also work.
So of course there's a big difference. One is about purchasing for
labor, that's money, the other is about marriage, so that could be
the act of sex. What type of קל וחומר Kal Vachomer is
that, just because that money works there doesn't mean money is going
to work here, right? So the גמרא Gemara says יבמה תוכיח, Yevamah
tochiach, let's prove from יבמה, Yevamah, שנקנית בביאה, she'niknes b'biah, there sex
works the act of יבום, Yibum, ואינה נקנית בכסף, ve'eina niknes b'kesef,
not money. Okay, so מה ליבמה שכן אינה נקנית בשטר, mah l'yevamah
she'ken eina niknes b'shtar, no, no, no, because a יבמה Yevamah
there's only one act, only the act of sex,
שטר Shtar doesn't
work. תאמר בזו שנקנית בשטר, Tomar b'zu she'niknes b'shtar, okay, whereas by,
we're going to learn now from a פסוק that marriage can work
with a שטר. Shtar. So if it can work with a שטר,
Shtar, it obviously works in broader areas than just יבום. Yibum. יבום
Yibum only works through ביאה, biah, marriage works through ביאה biah and
a שטר, Shtar, that's what we're going to learn those out. So
if it works through ביאה biah and a שטר, Shtar, let it
also work through כסף, Kessef and let's learn it out from אמה
עבריה. amah ivriya. So therefore then what does תלמוד לומר כי יקח
Talmud lomar Ki Yikach. איש? So we have a פסוק כי יקח
איש ki yikach ish? that we learn it out from אברהם Avraham
and
קיחה. kikha. says גמרא, Gemara this is a, this sometimes מדרש הלכה
Midrash Halakha goes like this. It's very bizarre, it's discontinuous. It says,
why did we need a פסוק? We could have made a קל
וחומר. Spells out the קל וחומר, and then says, and therefore we
have the פסוק. But you just said you had a קל וחומר,
you didn't answer why we needed the פסוק. So the גמרא Gemara
asks a question. So the גמרא Gemara says: היכא דמיקרא אתיא ליה?
Heicha d'meikra atya lei? You just learned it out from a קל
וחומר from אמה עברייה. Amivriyah. So אמר רב אשי: Amar Rav Ashi:
נא, na, משום דאיכא למימר מעיקרא דדינא פירכא, mishum de'ika lemeimar me'ikra
de'dina pircha, because you could ask from the source of the very
law, from אמה עברייה Amivriyah itself. והיכא קמאסית לה? Ve'heicha k'massit lah?
Where do you want to learn out that the כסף Kessef? should
work? מאמה עברייה, Me'Amivriyah, from an אמה עברייה. Amivriyah. מה אמה עברייה
שכן יוצאה בכסף? Ma Amivriyah sheken yotza be'Kessef? נא, Na, אמה עברייה,
Amivriyah, it makes sense that money works to acquire an אמה עברייה
Amivriyah because she goes free by giving money. Okay. תאמר בזו שאינה
יוצאה בכסף, Tomar be'zo she'eina yotza be'Kessef, right? In this one, right,
a woman doesn't go free by giving money back to her husband.
Right? So give me a פרוטה, Peruta, here's your ring back, here's
your פרוטה Peruta back, I'm now divorced. It doesn't work that way.
Okay. Which by the way again shows אמה עברייה Amivriyah is about
possession and acquisition, she's bought with money, she's freed with money. But
by a woman, since she's not freed with money, maybe she's not
bought with money either. Okay. תאמר Tomar so therefore you can't learn
her out from אמה עברייה. Amivriyah. תלמוד לומר talmud lomar כי יקח.
Ki Yikach Therefore it says כי יקח איש. ki yikach ish Now
again, this is such a beautiful גמרא Gemara in juxtaposition to the
previous one, right? Because the previous one the whole model was selling
the daughter and it was all about the father and his control
over her etc. Here, the whole point is, you know why you
need a פסוק by אברהם? Avraham? Because this isn't like a sale
of a slave. I'll tell you how it's not like a sale
of a slave. Because the sale of a slave is all about
money and what's the proof? She's sold with money and she's freed
with money. This woman isn't freed with money, so maybe logically she
shouldn't be sold with money. Okay. So it is exactly contrasting that
it's not about a sale and therefore you need the פסוק by
אברהם. Avraham. Now, what you might still say is okay, but at
the end of the day, the פסוק by אברהם Avraham is still
she's a field, she's being purchased like a field. It's still a
sale transaction. So תוספות Tosafos already points out, very interesting. What is
כי יקח Ki Yikach referring to by the case by אברהם? Avraham?
What's being taken by in the אברהם Avraham case? נתתי כסף השדה
קח ממני. Natati kessef hasadeh kach mimeni. What's being taken? The money,
not the field. Right? So taking the money. So the כי יקח
ki yikach so if you focus on not that the woman is
the field that's being possessed but כי יקח איש אשה, Ki Yikach
ish isha, oh it's funny she's the one taking the money. But
then again, maybe there's a way to learn that the focusing more
on the possessing of the money as the act, not the possessing
of the woman as the act. And again trying to make it
maybe more of a symbolic act than of something that's really about
possessing. Maybe it's a little bit of a דרוש. Drush. Okay. But
nevertheless, this דרוש Drush certainly of אברהם Avraham downplays the possession, buying,
transaction, and particularly the point, she's not freed with money, she shouldn't
be sold with money. The other thing to point out is that
she's an actor in this case. And I want to say and
I think that's why the גמרא Gemara at the beginning, right, remember
at the beginning it's all of oh, what do you mean where's
כסף? kessef קיחה קיחה משדה עפרון, Kicha kicha mi'Sdeh Efron, קיחה קיחה
משדה עפרון. Kicha kicha mi'Sdeh Efron. Like that was the resounding, the
echoing theme even though the גמרא Gemara just spent a whole big
discussion about the father model. Because at least in the קיחה קיחה
משדה עפרון, Kicha kicha mi'Sdeh Efron, you know you don't have somebody
else selling her. I mean you could say, well I don't know,
עפרון Efron is the owner and he's selling the field so it's
the father selling the daughter. But there really are only two people
in the אברהם Avraham story, right? And it more suggests a model
of the woman marrying herself. So even so there's two things about
that that I think are much more are in very strong contrast
to the father selling his daughter. I mean it's not slavery, it's
not emphasizing like she's an object, you know, it doesn't, you know
it has it's a better model, it's a much better model. And
I think it also like I said it that it doesn't have
her that you could imagine that that much more represents the woman
marrying herself rather than you know because there's only two players in
that as opposed to the father and daughter there are like three
players. There's the father selling the daughter and in the אברהם Avraham
and עפרון Efron there's only two players. So the גמרא Gemara. though
ends up by saying why do I need both פסוקים? pesukim What
I'll just find you. Anyways I have to I have to go
in like two minutes. Let's just get to the two dots. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this, okay. איצטריך למכתב ויצאה חנם ואיצטריך
למכתב כי יקח איש. Itztarich lemichtav veyatz'a chinam ve'itztarich lemichtav ki yikach
ish. דאי כתב רחמנא De'ei katav rachmana כי יקח ki yikach by
the כי יקח ki yikach and what we learned out from אברהם,
Avraham, הוה אמינא hava amina קידושין דיהיב בעל דדידה הוו. kiddushin d'yaiv
ba'al dedidah havoh.
I would have said okay I learn out there's קידושין kiddushin כסף
but maybe she keeps it because again the whole point of those
פסוקים is there's no father there. She's the actor. So maybe she
keeps the money even if as a נערה. We're back to the
נערה question. She does keep the money if she's a בוגרת. כתב
רחמנא ויצאה חנם Katav rachmana veyatz'a chinam
to tell me that as a even as a נערה the money
would go to the father. ואי כתב רחמנא ויצאה חנם Ve'ei katav
rachmana veyatz'a chinam had it told me that I would have thought
היכא דיהיב אינהו, heicha d'yaiv inhu, this is very interesting. If I
just had the פסוק by the father, by the ויצאה חנם, veyatz'a
chinam, I would have thought היכא דייהבא איהי לדידיה, heicha diyihava ihi
ledidei,
if maybe she gave the money to him וקידשתו vekidashto and she
married him, הוו קידושין? havei kiddushin? Because that doesn't tell you who's
buying whom, meaning it all says ויצאה חנם אין כסף, veyatzah chinam
ein kesef, so it means that in another time when she leaves
the father's control there is money. But how do I know how
the money works? Maybe she's the one that gives the money to
him. If you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says, where's רש"י?
Rashi? היכא דייהבא איהי לדידיה heicha diyihava ihi ledidei כסף וקידשתו kesef
vekidashto דאמרה ליה התקדש לי. deamrah lei hiskadesh li.
So maybe if she says to him, marry me, because all it
says is אין כסף, ein kesef, so maybe it's a transaction with
money, maybe it can go either way. Okay, so הוו קידושין. havei
kiddushin. כי יקח ki yikach no כי תקח. ki tikach. No,
he has to be the taker. So so much for me trying
to emphasize that the כי יקח model is very much different from
the possession transaction. Here the גמרא suggests at the end that the
whole slave model could have somehow still suggested, all it says is
that there's money. Maybe she's the one that does the act. Now
by the way I'll just end by reading this little תוספות Tosafos
and we'll end here for today. תוספות Tosafos says, look at תוספות
Tosafos היכא דייהבא איהי לדידיה וקידשתו, heicha diyihava ihi ledidei vekidashto, תוספות
Tosafos says, פירש בקונטרס שאומרת הרי אתה מקודש לי. perash bekuntres sheomeres
harei ata mekudash li. וקשה שהרי באיש אין נופל לשון קידושין שאין
נאסר בכך לשאר נשים, vekashah sheharei beish ein nofel lashon kiddushin sheein
neesar bekach leshaar nashim, right? Even if she could
be the actor, he's
fundamentally the status of being מקודשת mekudeshet is a status that applies
to her, because her status changes vis-a-vis other men. When he's married
to her, his status doesn't change to other people. Okay, which is
a very important point.
It's not just who does the act, it's a fundamental question of
who has the status change. ויש לפרש שאומרת הרי אני מקודשת לך.
veyesh levaresh sheomeres harei ani mekudeshet lach.
Okay fine. So she says, I'm מקודשת mekudeshet to you. She's still
the speaker. And then תוספות Tosafos goes one step further. וצריך לומר
דייהבא איהי לדידיה לאו דוקא. vetzarich lomar diyihava ihi ledidei lav davka.
Actually no, when the גמרא says she gives the money to him,
it didn't mean that. שהרי אביו מקבל קידושין. sheharei aviv mekabel kiddushin.
We just got through saying that the father receives the money. אלא
רוצה לומר ואמרה. ela rotzah lomar veamrah. So תוספות Tosafos says we
transform the whole גמרא as opposed to רש"י Rashi says that there
was a הוה אמינא hava amina she would give the money and
say הרי אתה מקודש לי, harei ata mekudash li, תוספות says no
no no, what it really means is he gives the money and
she still receives the money and she's just saying הרי אני מקודשת
לך. harei ani mekudeshet lecha. For תוספות it's a הוה אמינא hava
amina of נתן הוא ואמרה היא, nasan hu veamrah hi, which is
a סוגיא that we're gonna see later. But that's not פשט pshat
of the גמרא. So again, very interesting, these two different models and
at the very last minute the גמרא sort of suggests the איפכא
מסתברא ippcha mistavra of what I would have inferred from those two
models. Okay, we'll end with that.